Guide to the Jessica Burstein Photographs and Memorabilia 1940s-2017 (bulk 1970s-2012) PR 361
New-York Historical Society
Jessica Burstein photographs and memorabilia
1940s-2017 (bulk 1970s-2012)
New-York Historical Society
Burstein, Jessica
PR 361
43.5 Linear feet in 32 boxes of various sizes and three flat files
The collection consists principally of photographs taken by Jessica Burstein over the course of her career, which began in the mid-1970s at NBC-TV. Three primary subject areas are the construction of the new Yankee Stadium (2006-2009), patrons of Elaine's Restaurant (circa 1990-2011), and still shots from the set of the "Law & Order" television series (1992-circa 2008), including photographs of staged crime scenes she took for a 2003 book. Other subjects include photographs from the set of the "New York Undercover" television series and individual and group portraits from an array of political, entertainment, sports, and literary figures. The collection also holds an assortment of tee shirts, pins and other memorabilia related to the photographic subjects.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists principally of photographs taken by Jessica Burstein over the course of her career. Three primary subject areas are the construction of the new Yankee Stadium (2006-2009), patrons of Elaine's Restaurant (circa 1990-2011), and still shots from the set of the "Law & Order" television series (1992-circa 2008), including photographs of "Law & Order" staged crime scenes she took for a 2003 book.
Other subject areas dating from before, during and after her tenure with NBC include individual and group portraits of figures from politics, movies and television entertainment, music, sports, literature and journalism, business, and others. Her portfolio of images from the Sunny Atlantic Beach Club on Long Island and photographs from the television show "New York Undercover" are also in the collection.
In addition to photographs, the collection includes memorabilia related to the photographic subjects. Some of this is text-based, such as cast calls and other documents for "Law & Order" and other TV and movie sets. Other memorabilia includes tee shirts, caps, pins, and other items.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in six series:
I. Yankee Stadium Construction
II. Elaine's Restaurant
III. Law & Order
IV. New York Undercover
V. Sunny Atlantic Beach Club / Atlantic Beach Book
VI. Various Subjects
These series generally follow the subject categories as defined by the photographer, Jessica Burstein. For the first five series, with minor exception, the photographs remain in the boxes as presented to N-YHS by Burstein. There was no particular arrangement of the photographs in the original boxes; some slight rearrangement was done during processing.
The sixth series was a "mix" of subjects. The subject or context of some of these photos was identified by Burstein, but not for most. Accordingly, the processing archivist arranged much of this series.
Burstein's notes and captions are found on many of the photographs and on the boxes themselves. In April 2018, after the collection had been donated to N-YHS, Burstein went through many of the photographs to add identifying information where it was lacking; many of these added notes were written in blue pencil and are identifiable in that way.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the photographer, Jessica Burstein, in December 2017.
Credit line: Gift of Jessica Burstein.
Separated Materials
A portfolio by Bert Stern titled Levis in America was included by Burstein in her gift. Burstein told the processing archivist that this was given to her by Stern as an in-lieu payment for work done. The portfolio was separated and cataloged individually (PR 376).
Biographical / Historical
Jessica Burstein, born in Nassau County on Long Island, was educated in Switzerland and New York. From an early age she developed an interest in photography, having a dark room by age 11. She began her career in 1974 as the first female staff photographer for the NBC television network. She remained at NBC for about four years taking pictures of everything from news events, such as the 1976 Democratic National Convention, to television shows and movies, such as "Saturday Night Live" and the miniseries "King," about Martin Luther King, Jr. After leaving NBC, Burstein worked freelance on various projects and commissions.
Burstein is a member of an accomplished family, notably in the field of law. Both of her parents were lawyers; her mother, Beatrice S. Burstein, was a judge in the New York state system, becoming a member of the state Supreme Court in 1972. Burstein had four siblings, some of whom also entered the legal profession; these included her older sister, Karen Burstein, who has held positions in all three branches of New York state's government over the course of her career. So it is perhaps not surprising that, by the early 1990s, Jessica considered a switch to law when her photography career hit a dry spell. However, when she mentioned this to Elaine Kaufman, the owner of Elaine's Restaurant on New York's Upper East Side urged her to stay with photography and gave Burstein permission to take photographs in the restaurant, which Kaufman displayed on a wall there. Burstein continued to do so through the closing of the restaurant in 2011.
Burstein had been a regular at Elaine's since the 1970s as her photography career led her into the celebrity circles that frequented that place. Still, it was only in 1990 when Kaufman attended an exhibition of Burstein's work and acquired a triptych of her Truman Capote photographs that Kaufman began to engage with Burstein as a serious photographer and advocated for her work. It was through this connection with Kaufman and Burstein's exposure at the restaurant, that Dick Wolf, the executive producer of the Law & Order television series, asked Burstein to photograph the crime scenes staged for the show in anticipation of a book he visualized on the subject. Burstein took these pictures over the course of the next decade, which eventually led to the publication of "Law & Order: Crime Scenes" in 2003. Along the way, Burstein's role expanded to become the official photographer for Law & Order and its spin-offs through the 1990s and into the 2000s. Burstein was also the photographer for another Dick Wolf television production, New York Undercover.
Burstein's connection with Kaufman also led her to the commission to document a historic New York event: the construction of the new Yankee Stadium from 2006 to 2009. At Elaine's restaurant, Burstein had met George Steinbrenner, principal owner of the Yankees, and Randy Levine, the organization's president. On Burstein's occasional visits to the Steinbrenner suite, she would take photos that Steinbrenner liked. Consequently, Levine suggested that Burstein submit a proposal to get the commission to photograph the stadium construction project, which Burstein won.
Burstein's career includes other publications, exhibitions, and awards. The above items are emphasized in this note because they are the most relevant to the collection held by New-York Historical Society. In 2017, Burstein left New York to live in Camden, Maine. At that time, she donated to N-YHS that part of her work most related to New York City.
(The above note was based on various sources, including her biography on photoshelter.com; a 2015 interview with Straus Media; Burstein's reminiscences in Amy Philip Penn's "Elaine's: The Rise of One of New York's Most Legendary Restaurants"; a 2017 New York Times article; and others.)
Law & order (Television program); New York undercover (Television program); Anti-war demonstrations.; Authors -- Photographs.; Construction workers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Entertainers -- United States -- Photographs.; Musicians -- United States -- Photographs.; Political candidates.; Television actors and actresses -- Photographs.; Atlantic Beach (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Buttons (information artifacts); Photographs.; T-shirts.; Elaine's Restaurant (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Yankee Stadium (New York, N.Y.: 2009- ) -- Photographs.
- Series I. Yankee Stadium Construction, 2007-2010; 16.6 Linear feet
  Biographical / Historical
  The New York Yankees, under the leadership of principal owner George M. Steinbrenner III (often referred to as "The Boss"), constructed a new stadium for the baseball team from 2006-2009. Groundbreaking was on 16 August 2006. During construction, which ran through the 2007 and 2008 seasons, the Yankees continued to play in the old stadium, which was just a block or so away. The 2009 season was the first played in the new stadium, starting with Opening Day on 16 April 2009. The Yankees had a successful year, winning the World Series (their 27th championship) in their first year in the new ballpark. The Yankees' opponent in the Series were the Philadelphia Phillies; the final, clinching game of the Series was played at the new stadium. Among the Yankees' leading players on that team were the "Core Four" of Derek Jeter, Andy Pettite, Mariano Rivera, and Jorge Posada, as well as Mark Teixeira, Alex Rodriguez, and others.
  Scope and Contents
  The series primarily consists of 1000 color photographs, principally of the construction of the new Yankee Stadium from 2007-2009 (most of the photographs are undated so it is not clear if any date from the earliest construction in 2006). The bulk are 11x14 inches, though there are several larger and smaller in size. The construction photos provide both panoramic views of the work's progress, as well as detailed views of particular aspects of the work, such as placing the signage in the outfield, laying the turf, unboxing the memorials moved from Monument Park, and doing ironwork. Close-ups of construction workers appear frequently. While the crews consisted mostly of men, several women crew members are found in the images as well.
  In addition to the construction, there are photographs from the Yankees' opening season at the new park, as well as some final photos of the last days in the old Yankee Stadium. Shots from the Yankees' World Series appearance are in the series. Derek Jeter appears in many of these photos, and other then-current players appear as well. Former players, including Yogi Berra and Reggie Jackson, appear in some photos, as do other notables, such as George Steinbrenner, Donald Trump, Rudy Giuliani, and Michael Bloomberg.
  In addition to photographs, the series holds some memorabilia, including a poster, pins, a tee shirt, and some documents.
  Arrangement
  Most of the photographs remain in the boxes as received from the photographer. There is no particular order to them within boxes or across them. There are multiple prints of the same image, often found in various boxes and sizes. During processing, photographs signed by Burstein or annotated were placed at the front of the boxes. Also pulled together in this way were photos of game action, players, notable people, crowds at games, and other such photos not related to the construction process.
  In the inventory below, the first nine boxes hold the 11x14 (and some 8x10) prints. These are followed by a box and a flat file of larger prints, and memorabilia.
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 1 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 1)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 2 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 2)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 3 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 3)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 4 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 4)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 5 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 5)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 6 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 6)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 7 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 7)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 8 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 8)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Box 9 of 9), 2007-2009 (Box 9)
  - Yankee Stadium Construction Photographs (Flat box), 2007-2009 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Yankee Stadium Photographs, 2007-2009 (Folder FF-1)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Includes five color photographs on foamcore. Unframed by Alan Balicki, April 2018.
    32 x 53 inch: Image of letter Y being lowered to complete the stadium signage for the word "Yankee."
    36 x 24 inch: 1) Monuments on the move: Gehrig monument shrinkwrapped and boxed, Ruth monument on pallet; 2) rooftop workers lowering the "A" in Yankee Stadium signage into place.
    25 x 18 inch: 1) "A.J. Burnett practise [warm-up] pitch, World Series Game 2." Signed. Dated 2009; and 2) "Dugout, Yankee Stadium, 2009" signed [Includes players Derek Jeter, Johnny Damon, Mariano Rivera, among others].
  - Poster: "I was a flusher at 'The Big Flush' The New Yankee Stadium, February 28, 2009" (Flat box) (Box 31, Folder 1)
    Caption on back provided by Burstein in April 2018: "Yankee Stadium, Day all toilets were tested by flushing at once." Autographed by the flushers, including Plumbers Local Union No. 1. approx 22x17.
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 2006, 2010 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Two documents: press kit for the new stadium's groundbreaking ceremony (2006) and "The Yankees Magazine" (October 2010). The press kit is still sealed, but the press release and program that were inside the kit were removed by the processing archivist and are in the folder as well.
  - Tee Shirt, 2009 (Box 30)
    Long sleeve T-shirt celebrating the Ironworkers Local 580 work on the new stadium, 2006-2009.with Yankees logo
  - Pins, 2007-2010 (Box 26)
    5 pins, commemorating: the construction completion date of 17 February 2009 (2 pins); All-Star Game (2008); Postseason (2010); and Yankees-Boston Red Sox rivalry (2007).
- Series II. Elaine's Restaurant, circa 1990-2008; 5.2 Linear feet
  "Elaine's" was a bar and restaurant on New York City's Upper East Side, at 2nd Avenue and East 88th Street. It was named after its owner, Elaine Kaufman (1929-2010). Begun by Kaufman in 1963, the restaurant was a favorite spot of celebrities. Kaufman died in December 2010, and the restaurant closed a few months later.
  The series holds several hundred photographs (though many are duplicate prints) taken by Burstein at Elaine's during the 1990s and 2000s. The bulk are black and white, though there are some color photographs.
  These are primarily casual posed shots of the restaurant's patrons. Burstein identified the subjects for many of the photos, which include authors/literary figures/journalists (e.g., Truman Capote, William Styron, George Plimpton, Graydon Carter, Salman Rusdie, David Halberstam, Walter Mosley, Molly Ivins, etc.), sports figures (e.g., Keith Hernandez, Chuck Daly, George Steinbrenner, etc.), actors/entertainers (e.g., Ben Kingsley, Chris Noth, Clint Eastwood, Forest Whitaker, Michael Caine, Henry Mancini, Don Rickles, Sigourney Weaver, Gwyneth Paltrow, Russell Simmons, Helen Mirrer, etc.), TV personalities (e.g., Joan Rivers, Dr. Ruth Westheimer, Geraldo Rivera, etc.), entertainment executives/producers/directors/agents (e.g., Harvey Weinstein, Roger Altman, Sydney Pollack, James Woods, etc.), politicians/government figures (e.g., Robert Morgenthau, John McCain, Michael Bloomberg, David Dinkins, etc.), among others.
  Although the bulk of the photographs focus on the patrons, some do capture views of the interior of the bar and restaurant itself. Elaine appears in many of the photographs. Staff members also appear in some. The series also holds some memorabilia.
  The series opens with three boxes of photographs that are primarily 11x14 inches in size; most of the photographs remain in the boxes as received from the photographer. These are followed by photographs of somewhat larger size and by memorabilia.
  - Photographs at Elaine's (Box 1 of 3), 1990s-2000s (Box 10)
    In addition to the black and white photos found in all the boxes, this box holds several color photographs. There is also one photo autographed by Gay Talese and inscribed/autographed by Nan Talese.
  - Photographs at Elaine's (Box 2 of 3), 1990s-2000s (Box 11)
  - Photographs at Elaine's (Box 3 of 3), 1990s-2000s (Box 12)
  - Photographs at Elaine's (Flat box), 1990-2005 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    Holds several photographs:
    * 3 photographs, labeled by Burstein as "Capote triptych. Fiber prints (silver) on wall at Elaine's." Each signed and dated (1990). Each noted as "1/2 AP" and location within triptych identified. Approx. 24x10. Unframed by Alan Balicki April 2018. A portion of the original backing, with caption, is in the box. Also, a color photograph of the wall at Elaine's showing the original triptych is included with the three photographs.
    * Labeled by Burstein as "Truman Capote & Jake Snake. Fiber portrait (silver) on wall at Elaine's." Signed and dated (1990). Noted as "1/2 AP". Approx 20x24. Unframed by Alan Balicki April 2018. A portion of the original backing, with caption, is in the box.
    * Color photo of Elaine with George Steinbrenner (2005), inscribed and signed by Elaine.
    * Color photo of Elaine holding photo of Clint Eastwood at entrance to Elaine's (2005). The Eastwood photo and a portion of its original backing, with caption, is also in the box.
    * 3 other prints of photographs found in other boxes.
  - Photographs at Elaine's (Flat box), undated (Box 32, Folder 5)
    Holds six black and white 20x16 photographs, on boards, signed and captioned by Burstein:. Warren Hinckle, with dog Melman; George Plimpton; Ben Kingsley; Vince Curatola, Jessie Joyner, John Miller; Dr. Ruth with Joan Rivers; and Dabney Coleman.
  - Posters (3), 2005(?), 2007, 2008 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    Posters publicizing New Year's Eve at Elaine's (2005 or 2006, and 2007) and poster for Elaine's 45th anniversary event (2008).
  - Poster: "Elaine's 30th Anniversary", 1994 May (Folder FF-2)
    Inscribed and autographed by Elaine. Approximately 30x23 inches.
  - Table Check Stubs; Cafe Tallulah Publicity, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Books, 2004, 2015 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    Two books: "Everyone comes to Elaine's" by A.E. Hotchner and "Elaine's: the rise of one of New York's most legendary restaurants from those who were there" by Amy Phillips Penn. The Hotchner book is inscribed to Hal by Elaine. Both books include photographs by Burstein; the Penn book includes two articles written by Burstein. Both books are also held in N-YHS's main collection.
  - Solicitation Brochure and Program Booklet. Table 4 Writers Foundation First Annual Awards Gala, 2013 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Tee Shirt, 2011 (Box 30)
    T-shirt with saying "I closed Elaine's, 1963-2011"
  - Sign (from Elaine's?), 2011? (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Small metal sign "We are not responsible for personal property -- The Mgt."
- Series III. Law & Order, 1993-circa 2008; 10.6 Linear feet
  The television show "Law & Order" premiered on the NBC network on 13 September 1990. It would run for 20 seasons, until 2010, totalling 456 episodes, making it one of the longest running primetime TV series in American history. The one hour episodes would open with the discovery of a crime (typically a murder), with the balance of the time split between the police investigation and arrest of a suspect and the ensuing prosecution and trial. The show was so successful that it became a "brand" with spin-offs: "Law & Order: Criminal Intent" (2001-2011), "Law & Order: Trial by Jury" (2005-2006), "Law & Order: LA" (2010-2011), and "Law & Order: Special Victims Unit," which began in 1999 and remains on the air as of 2018. There was also a 1998 movie "Exiled: A Law & Order Movie," starring Chris Noth, who appeared on the TV show for its first five seasons.
  Over the years, the show's cast constantly evolved. Some of its major longstanding stars, who appear in Burstein's photographs here, include S. Epatha Merkerson (17 seasons), Sam Waterson (16 seasons), Jerry Orbach (12 seasons), Steven Hill (10 seasons), and Jesse L. Martin (9 seasons).
  In 1993, the producer of "Law & Order,"'s producer, Dick Wolf, approached Jessica Burstein to photograph the show's crime scenes, which she did over the course of the next several years. These were eventually formed into a book by Wolf and Burstein: "Law & Order: Crime Scenes," published by Barnes & Noble Books in 2003. In addition to her crime scene assignment, Burstein's role was also expanded to be a unit photographer for the show.
  (The above note was based primarily on information from NBC's website and the introduction to Dick Wolf's crime scenes book.)
  The series includes photographs, documents and memorabilia related to the show and spin-offs.
  A large number of the photographs are of the show's set, cast, and crew. Individuals represented are, among others, cast members Steven Hill, Chris Noth, Jerry Orbach, Sam Waterston, Ben Bratt, S. Epatha Merkerson, Dann Florek, Jill Hennessy, Jesse L. Martin, Carey Lowell, Angie Harmon, Bebe Neuwirth, Elisabeth Rohm, and Fred Thompson; guest stars William Kunstler, Fran Lebowitz, Laura Linney, and Elizabeth Ashley; producer Dick Wolf; and others. Some of the photographs are in color. Holds both 8x11 and 14x11 inch photographs.
  Other photographs are of the crime scenes from various shows. These photographs depict the victim as presented in the show itself, along with images concerning the creation of the scene (make-up being applied, positioning and framing of the body, etc.). Book drafts, mock-ups, proposal, as well as the final published version of "Law & Order: Crime Scenes" are in the series.
  The series holds a few documents including crew lists, a script and others. Some of these relate to "Law & Order: Criminal Intent." And the series holds some memorabilia. The documents and memorabilia are identified in the container list below.
  The series is arranged by format, beginning with photographs, then documents and memorabilia.
  - Photographs. Law & Order (Box 13)
    Includes both 8x11 and 14x11 inch photographs of the show's set, cast, and crew. Some color.
  - Photographs. Law & Order (Box 14)
    Primarily includes photographs of the set, cast and crew, with some crime scene photographs. Includes both 8x11 and 14x11, with some color. One color photograph of actor Christopher Lloyd as a magician (2008) is inscribed to Burstein and autographed.
  - Photograph. Law & Order Cast on Jill Hennessy's Last Day (Flat box), 1996 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Photographs. Law & Order. "The last goodbye. Jerry Orbach leaves Law & Order, May 2004." (Folder FF-3)
    Diptych, approximately 26x17 inches, on foamcore. Color photographs with Jerry Orbach, Jesse L. Martin and S. Epatha Merkerson. Unframed by Alan Balicki, April 2018.
  - Photographs. Law & Order: Criminal Intent. (Flat box), circa 2005 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    Two large color photographs: "Set in Rain" (2005) and a pitbull arena/crime scene (undated).
  - Photographs. "Law & Order: Crime Scenes." (Box 15)
    Primarily includes photographs, mock-ups, proofs, and other material related to the book "Law & Order: Crime Scenes" written by Dick Wolf, with photos by Burstein. Also a tear sheet and a publicity piece for an exhibition (2005) related to the book at George Eastman House. Some general cast shots are in this box as well.
  - Photographs. "Law & Order: Crime Scenes" (8x10) (Box 23)
    Holds the final book prints, used and not used.
  - Photographs. "Law & Order: Crime Scenes" (8x10) (Box 22)
    Holds photos of crime scenes, not necessarily used in the book.
  - Photographs. "Law & Order: Crime Scenes" (Flat box), circa 2003 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    Diptych of color photographs of bloodied faces for crime scenes.
  - Photographs. "Law & Order Crime Scenes." Oversize Photo Proof Sheets, 2003 (Folder FF-2)
    Two large sheets with multiple photographs from the book.